Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
翻译&&时间轴：邓雄飞、张大伟
压制&&特效：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
校对：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
特别感谢：裘宗燕教授
计算机程序的构造和解释
元循环求值器 I
Metacircular Evaluator
教授：今天我们将学习一些
PROFESSOR: Well today we're going to learn about something
非同一般的东西
quite amazing.
我们将对计算机程序
We're going to understand what we mean by a program
有更深层次的理解
a little bit more profoundly than we have up till now.
目前为止 我们一直把程序看作
Up till now, we've been thinking
对机器的描述
programs as describing machines.
举个例子 在这个幻灯片上
So for example, looking at this still store
我们可以看到一个计算阶乘的程序
we see here is a program for factorial.
当然 你可以认为这些字符串描述了
And what it is, is a character string description, if you will,
这个线路图所表示的无穷机器
of the wiring diagram of a potentially infinite machine.
我们可以稍稍地看下 它描述的是什么
And we can look at that a little bit and just see the idea.
这种紧凑的记法 描述的是：
That this is a sort of compact notation which says,
如果N是0 结果就是1
if n is 0, the result is one.
N是从这里进入机器的
Well here comes n coming into this machine,
如果它是0的话
and if it's 0,
那么我就控制这个开关
then I control this switch
把它掰到输出为1的那一端
in such a way that the switch allows the output to be one.
否则的话
Otherwise,
就是(* N (FACT (- N 1)))
it's n times factorial of n minus one.
我先计算(FACT (- N 1))
Well, I'm computing factorial of n minus one
再把结果乘以N
and multiplying that by n,
这样如果N不为0的话
in the case that it's not 0,
这个开关就会输出这里的结果
this switch makes the output come from there.
当然了
Of course,
这个机器可能有无穷多个部件
this is a machine with a potentially infinite number of parts,
因为FACT内部又调用了FACT
because factorial occurs within factorial,
因此我们不知道调用栈有多深
so we don't know how deep it has to be.
但到目前为止
But that's basically what our notation
代码对我们来说就是这样的东西了
for programs really means to us at this point.
你可以认为代码是用字符串来描述
It's a character string description, if you will,
某种用其它方式描画的线路图
of a wiring diagram that could also be drawn some other way.
事实上 很多人都向我提议
And, in fact, many people have proposed to me,
说程序设计语言应该像这个一样 是图像化的
programming languages look graphical like this.
不过我不认为用图形表示会有很多优势
I'm not sure I believe there are many advantages.
当然 最主要的劣势就是
The major disadvantage, of course,
它需要占用很大的平面空间
is that it takes up more space on a page,
所以展示和修改起来就非常麻烦
and, therefore, it's harder to pack into a listing or to edit very well.
但是不管怎样
But in any case,
在计算的世界中
there's something very remarkable
还有一个非常重要的东西
that can happen in the computation world
也就是所谓的“通用机器”
which is that you can have something called a universal machine.
我们再来看第二张幻灯片
If we look at the second slide,
我们看到的就是
what we see is
名为EVAL的特殊机器
a special machine called eval.
这个叫做EVAL的机器
There is a machine called eval,
也就是我今天要讲解的
and I'm going to show it to you today.
它非常简单
It's very simple.
最了不起的是 它简单得可以写在黑板上
What is remarkable is that it will fit on the blackboard.
然而 EVAL这个机器
However, eval is a machine
是以其它机器的描述作为输入的
which takes as input a description of another machine.
它可以接收一个
It could take the wiring diagram
阶乘机器的线路图作为输入
of a factorial machine as input.
这样一来
Having done so,
它就可以模拟那台阶乘机器
it becomes a simulator for the factorial machine
这样的话
such that,
如果输入6 就会得到720
if you put a six in, out comes a 720.
这是一个非常了不起的机器
That's a very remarkable sort of machine.
而最让人惊奇的是
And the most amazing part of it
它竟然可以写在一个黑板内
it is that it fits on a blackboard.
与之相反的是
By contrast,
我们可以想象一下模拟电子世界中的
one could imagine in the analog electronics world
一台非常不同的机器
a very different machine.
这台机器呢
a machine where, a machine
某种意义上 同样也是“通用机器”
which also was, in some sense, universal,
只要你输入一个电路图
where you gave a circuit diagram as one of the inputs,
比如这个小型的低通滤波器
for example, of this little low-pass filter,
单极低通滤波器之类的
one-pole low-pass filter.
你可以想像
And you can imagine that
如果我们扫描这个元件得到扫描线
you could, for example, scan this out-- the scan lines
得到的信号描述的就是
Right? are the signal that's describing
这个机器所模拟的
what this machine is to simulate--
这个模拟机器EVAL是由电路构成
then the analog of eval which is made out of electrical circuits,
它可以把自己配置成一个滤波器
which configure itself into a filter
响应由电路图指定的频率
has the frequency response specified by the circuit diagram.
这种机器很难制造出来
That's a very hard machine to make,
当然 更不可能用一个黑板就把它说清楚
and, surely, there's no chance that I could put it on a blackboard.
所以今天我们将学习一些神奇的东西
So we're going to see an amazing thing today.
我们将在黑板上见证
We're going to see, on the blackboard,
通用机器
the universal machine.
跟其它程序比起来
And we'll see that among other things,
它真是非常简单
it's extremely simple.
现在 我们已经非常接近
Now, we're getting very close
计算机中真正的精灵了
the real spirit in the computer at this point.
所以为了保持足够的尊重
So I have to show a certain amount of reverence and respect,
我特地穿上外套
so I'm going to wear a suit jacket for the only time
你们应该从没见我穿过
that you'll ever see me wear a suit jacket here.
在这个盛重的场合
And I think I'm also going to
我还得戴上一顶合适的帽子
put on an appropriate hat for the occasion.
开讲前再给大家提个醒
Now, this is a lecturer which I have to warn you--
那些40岁以下
let's see, normally, people under 40
以及没有孩子的人
and who don't have several children
你们可要小心了
are advised to be careful.
如果真的受不了 可以选择离开
If they're really worried, they should leave.
因为一会儿要发生一些
Because there's a certain amount of
非常神秘的事情
mysticism that will appear here
可能使你的大脑异常混乱
which may be disturbing and cause trouble in your minds.
好了 无论如何
Well in any case, let's see,
我要带着你们写一个Lisp求值器
I wish to write for you the evaluator for Lisp.
求值器并不复杂
Now the evaluator isn't very complicated.
很像我们以前见到过的程序
It's very much like all the programs we've seen already.
这也是它令人吃惊的地方
That's the amazing part of it.
现在我开始写这个程序
It's going to be-- and I'm going to write it right here--
我把这个程序叫做EVAL
it's a program called eval.
这个过程接收两个参数
And it's a procedure of two arguments
表达式EXP和环境ENV
expression and an environment.
跟所有实用过程一样
And like every interesting procedure,
它是个“按情况分析”语句
it's a case analysis.
但是在我开始之前
But before I start on this,
我还想你们注意一下
I want to tell you some things.
我将要在黑板上写的程序
The program we're going to write on the blackboard
非常丑陋、混乱、令人作呕
is ugly, dirty, disgusting,
并不是一种专业的写法
not the way I would write this is a professional.
它是用具体语法写就的
It is written with concrete syntax,
也就是说用了很多CAR、CDR
meaning you've got really to use lots of CARs and CDRs
我之前告诉过你们这样写并不好
which is exactly what I told you not to do.
在这里是故意这样来写的
That's on purpose in this case,
因为我想让它尽量精简
because I want it to be small, compact,
能塞在黑板内
fit on the blackboard
你们就可以看到整个代码
so you can get the whole thing.
我就不像平时那样实用长变量名了
So I don't want to use long names like I normally use.
就用CAR、CDR 因为它们短小
I want to use CAR-CDR because it's short.
这算是一种取舍
Okay, I wanna, it's a whole, that's a trade-off.
我不希望你们这样来写程序
I don't want you writing programs like this.
这里单纯地想达到一种简洁的效果
This is purely for an effect.
因此你们读起来可能有些费力
Now, you're going to have to work a little harder to read it,
我尽量写得清楚一些
but I'm going to try to make it clear as I'm writing it.
这个解释器已经比较完整了
I'm also-- this is a pretty much complete interpreter,
但是还是缺少一些功能
but there's going to be room for putting in more things--
我就不写定义和赋值的部分了
I'm going to leave out definition and assignment,
因为它们都不是最本质的
just because they are not essential,
稍后我就会解释 这是数学上的原因
and a, for a mathematical reason I'll show you later
当然啦 黑板也没有那么大
and also they take up more space.
但是 我们怎么做呢？
But, in any case, what do we have to do?
我们需要一个分派
We have to do a dispatch
它根据表达式的类型
which breaks the types of expressions up
把它们划分为几类
into particular classes.
这就是现在要做的
Okay? So that's what we're going to have here.
我们都有哪些表达式？
Well, what expressions are there?
我们先来看几种表达式
Let's look at the kinds of expressions.
比如说 数字“3”就是一个表达式
We can have things like the numeral three.
我想让它代表什么呢？
What do I want that to do?
我有很多选择 但是就现在而言
I can make choices, but I think right now,
我就想让它表示数字3
I want it to be a three.
这就是我要的
That's what I want.
这个足够简单
So that's easy enough.
那就意味着 如果表达式是数字
That means I want, if the thing is a number,
表达式本身就应该是求值结果
that I want the expression itself as the answer.
另外一种情况是
Now the next possibility
表达式还可能是符号
is things that we represent as symbols.
比如EXP、ENV、EVAL、NUMBER、X之类
Examples of symbols are things like x, n, eval, number, x.
它们意味着什么？
What do I mean them to be?
它们是一类代表其它事物的事物
Those are things that stand for other things.
也就是我们语言中所谓的变量
Those are the variables of our language.
因此我想要能够 比如说
And so I want to be able to say, for example,
对X求值 可能会得到3
that x, for example, transforms to it's value which might be three.
又可能是CAR
Or I might ask something like car.
我希望它的值是
I want to have as its value--
某种类似于过程的东西
be something like some procedure,
我不需要知道它内部是什么
which I don't know what is inside there,
可能是一些机器码 或者类似的东西
perhaps a machine language code or something like that.
到这是还是相对简单的
Ok? So, well, that's easy enough.
我想把这部分交给其他人来写
I'm going to push that off on someone else.
如果我们有一个符号
If something is a symbol,
假如表达式是符号
if the expression is a symbol,
那么我求值它的结果就应该是
then I want the answer to be the result,
在环境ENV中查找该表达式的值
looking up the expression in the environment.
环境是一个字典
Now the environment is a dictionary
它把符号映射成一个值
which maps the symbol names to their values.
就这么简单
And that's all it is.
怎么完成的呢？
How it's done?
稍后我们再谈这个
Well, we'll see that later.
其实并不难
It's very easy.
编写类似于表的数据结构非常容易
It's easy to make data structures that are tables of various sorts.
但它只是一个表
But it's only a table,
而这是存取某个表的过程
and this is the access routine for some table.
好的 接下来
Ok? Well, the next thing,
另一类表达式
another kind of expression--
表达式可能是一些不是数字的常量
you have things that are described constants that are not numbers,
比如 'FOO
like 'foo.
为了方便起见
Well, for my convenience,
我想在语法上
I want to syntactically transform that
把它转换成表结构
into a list structure which is,
比如说是(QUOTE FOO)
which is, quote foo.
一个被引用起来的对象 无论它是什么
Or it's -- A quoted object, whatever it is,
都实际上是一个缩写
is going to be actually an abbreviation,
这一部分并不由求值器负责
which is not part of the evaluator
这是在其它地方完成的
but happens somewhere else,
左边的符号就是右边表达式的缩略形式
an abbreviation for an expression that looks like this.
这样 我就可以
This way, I can test for
依据表达式的CAR部分
the type of the expression as being a quotation
来判断它的类型了
by examining the car of the expression.
因此这一部分也不会出现在求值器中
So I'm not going to worry about that in the evaluator.
这在更早时候
It's happening somewhere earlier
比如源代码读取阶段完成
in the reader or something.
如果是引用表达式
If the expression of the expression is quote,
那么求值的结果就是
then what I want,
我想让(QUOTE FOO)求值为自身FOO
I want quote foo to itself evaluate to foo.
一个常量
It's a constant.
这条代码是说
This is just a way of saying
这类表达式求值为它自己
that this evaluates to itself.
怎么才能把它取出来呢？
Ok? So thats the. What is that?
这是列表第二个元素的第一个部分
That's the first of the second of the list.
也就是表的第二个元素
That's the second of the list.
也就是CADR
The second element of the list is it's CADR.
所以这里我就写CADR
So I'm just going to write here, CADR.
表达式还可能是什么类型呢？
OK? What else do we have here?
还有LAMBDA表达式
We have lambda expressions,
比如 (LAMBDA (X) (+ X Y))
for example, lambda of x plus x y.
我还得找到某种表示方法
Well, I going have to have some representation for the procedure
LAMBDA表达式求值的结果
which is the value of an expression,
也就是如何表示过程
of a lambda expression.
过程并不就是表达式(LAMBDA (x))
The procedure here is not the expression lambda x.
表达式只是过程的代码描述
That's the description of it, the textual description.
如果在词法作用域的语言中实现过程
However, what what I going to expect to see here
那么我希望在表示过程的时候
is something which contains an environment as one of its parts
能够把当前的求值环境包括进来
if I'm implementing a lexical language.
所以这里我还需要
And so what I'd like to see
一些类型标志
is some type flags.
这样后面我就可以用它们来区分过程
I'm going to have to be able to distinguish procedures later,
看哪些是由LAMBDA表达式生成的
procedures which were produced by lambdas,
哪些是基本过程
from ones that may be primitive.
所以这里是个类型标志
And so I'm going to have some flag,
出于历史原因
which I'll just arbitrarily call closure,
我用CLOSURE作为类型标志
just for historical reasons.
现在来看看 哪部分比较重要
Now, to say what parts of this are important.
我需要知道
I'm going to need to know
绑定变量表和过程的体
the bound variable list and the body.
这是它的CDR部分
Well, that's the CDR of this,
这里就是((X) (+ X Y))
so it's going to be x and plus x y and some environment.
以及某个环境
and some environment.
用户不应该看到这个东西
Now this is not something that users should ever see,
这只是过程对象的
this is purely a representation, internally,
一种内部表示
for a procedure object.
它包括绑定变量表
It contains a bound variable list,
过程的体和某个环境
a body, and an environment,
以及一个类型标签 表示这是一个过程
and some type tag saying, I am a procedure.
接下来写代码
I'm going to make one now.
如果表达式的CAR部分是'LAMBDA
So if the CAR of the expression is quote lambda,
这里 我就要
then what I'm going to put here
创建一个表 表头是'CLOSURE
is-- I'm going to make a list of closure,
接着是 过程代码的CDR部分
the CDR of the procedure description
也就是除开LAMBDA的其它部分
was everything except the lambda,
以及当前的环境
and the current environment.
这样就实现了环境模型中的那些规则
This implements the rule for environments in the environment model.
这是从LAMBDA表达式中构建过程所必须遵守的
It has to do with construction of procedures from lambda expressions.
那个求值器在遇到
The environment that was around
LAMBDA表达式时的环境
at the time the evaluator encountered the lambda expression
在过程运行的时候
is the environment where the lambda expression gets
会去这个环境中查找自由变量的值
where the procedure resulting interprets it's free variables.
所以需要把它囊括进来
So that's part of that.
因此我们必须把求值时的环境
And so we have to capture that environment
作为过程对象的一部分
as part of the procedure object.
之后再来看它的作用
And we'll see how that gets used later.
我们也有COND表达式
There are also conditional expressions
像是(COND (P1 E1) (P2 E2) ...)这样的
of things like COND of say, p one, e one, p two, e two.
P1是谓词
Where this is a predicate,
谓词总是返回TRUE或者FALSE
a predicate is a thing that is either true or false,
如果谓词P1为真时 表达式E1才被求值
and the expression to be evaluated if the predicate is true.
当然 你也可以列这么一组子句
A set of clauses, if you will, that's the name for such a thing.
我会把它封装在另一个过程中
So I'm going put that somewhere else.
我们稍后在那个过程中进行处理
We're going to worry about that in another piece of code.
如果表达式的CAR部分是'COND的话
So EQ--  if the CAR of the expression is COND,
那么我就用EVCOND来求值这个表达式
then I'm going to do nothing more than evaluate the COND,
求值表达式的CDR部分
the CDR of the expression.
记得带上环境
That's all the clauses in the environment that I'm given.
好的 还有一种情况
Well, there's one more case,
任意的像(+ X 3)这样的表达式
arbitrary thing like the sum of x and three,
这是把运算符应用在运算对象上
where this is an operator applied to operands,
这并没有什么特殊的
and there's nothing special about it.
就是说 它不属于这里的特殊形式
It's not one of the special cases, the special forms.
上面写的这些都是特殊形式
These are the special forms.
再说明一下 如果我要把这个程序写得专业一点
And if I were writing here a professional program, again,
我会把它设计成数据导向的
I would somehow make this data directed.
那样的话 这里就不会是一系列的条件判断
So there wouldn't be a sequence of conditionals here,
而是根据一些比特位来做分派
there'd be a dispatch on some bits
这样来设计会更加专业一些
if I were trying to do this in a more professional way.
并且 我不用大量修改程序
So that, in fact, I can add to the thing
就可以添加规则
without changing my program much.
这样来做可能运行得更快
So, for example, they would run fast,
但这里我并不打算这么做
but I'm not worried about that.
现在的目的是把握EVAL过程的整体
Here we're trying to look at this in its entirety.
那么 最后一种情况
So it's else.
要怎么做呢？
Well, what do we do?
在这种情况下 我需要进行加法运算
In this case, I have to somehow do an addition.
那么我就得搞清楚 '+到底是什么
Well, I could find out what the plus is.
我还得知道X和3又代表什么
I have to find out what the x and the three are.
然后再把'+的所代表的东西
And then I have to apply the result of finding what the plus is
应用于'X与3所代表的东西上
to the result of finding out what the x and the three are.
具体来写一下
We'll have a name for that.
我要把表达式CAR部分的求值结果
So I'm going to apply the result of evaluating the CAR
应用在
of the expression--
表达式的CAR部分就是运算符
the car of the expression is the operator--
要在给定的环境中进行
in the environment given.
对运算符求值会得到一个过程
So evaluating the operator gets me the procedure.
现在 我要求值所有运算对象来取得参数
Now I have to evaluate all the operands to get the arguments.
我将调用EVLIST
I'll call that EVLIST,
来求值表达式的CDR部分 也就是运算对象
the CDR of the operands, of the expression,
当然是在相应的环境中
with respect to the environment.
我们待会儿再定义EVLIST
EVLIST will come up later--
（闭合括号中）
EVLIST, apply, COND pair, COND, lambda, define.
你现在看到的
So that what you are seeing here
基本上就是一个完整的求值器
is pretty much all there is in the evaluator itself.
它根据表达式的类型分情况处理
It's the case dispatch on the type of the expression
默认的情况是
with the default
表达式应用或者说是组合式
being a general application or a combination.
不过还有好些过程 我们没有定义
Now there is lots of things we haven't defined yet.
接下来就看这些未定义的部分
Let's just look at them and see what they are.
我们还要定义EVCOND
We're going to have to do this later, evcond.
我得定义APPLY
We have to write apply.
还有EVLIST
We're going to have to write EVLIST.
以及LOOKUP
We're going to write LOOKUP.
我看看 没别的了吧？
I think that's everything, isn't there?
剩下的东西都很简单
Everything else is something which is simple,
比如基本元素之类的东西
or primitive, or something like that.
当然
And, of course,
在这里 可以扩充很多特殊形式
we could many more special forms here,
但如果在通用语言中这么做就很糟糕
but that would be a bad idea in general in a language.
在这里添加大量的东西
You make a language very complicated
会让语言变得复杂
by putting a lot of things in there.
语言中的保留字
The number of reserve words that should exist in a language
不该比你能用几个手指、脚指记住的数目多
should be no more than a person could remember on his fingers and toes.
有些语言的保留字有成百上千个
And I get very upset with languages
我都不知道该说什么了
which have hundreds of reserve words.
保留字就是在这里定义的
But that's where the reserve words go.
好 接下来 我们来看下一个部分
Okay. Well, now let's get to the next part of this,
求值器的核心 APPLY
the kernel, apply.
它还做些什么呢？
What else is this doing?
APPLY把还是符号状态的求值运算符和运算对象
Well, apply's job is to take a procedure and apply it to its arguments
求值为相应的过程以及参数值
after both have been evaluated to come up with a procedure and the arguments
然后把得到的过程应用在参数上
rather the operator symbols and the operand symbols,
无论它们是什么符号表达式
whatever they are-- symbolic expressions.
我们把APPLY定义为
So we will define apply
接收两个参数的过程
to be a procedure of two arguments,
一个过程和对应的参数
a procedure and arguments.
它要怎么做呢？
And what does it do?
其实并不复杂
It does nothing very complicated.
分两种情况就够了
It's got two cases.
如果这个过程是基本过程--
Either the procedure is primitive--
我不知道这个谓词具体是如何判断的
And I don't know exactly how that is done.
可能这里面有某种类型信息
It's possible there's some type information
就像我们在这里用'CLOSURE
just like we made closure for, here,
来描述一些复合对象一样
being the description of the type of a compound thing--
我想可能是这样
OK? probably so.
但是具体怎么判断并不重要
But it is not essential how that works,
事实上
in fact, it turns out,
你可能已经知道或者推断过
as you probably know or have deduced,
我们并不需要任何基本过程
that you don't need any primitives anyway.
就算没有它们 照样可以进行计算
You can compute anything because without
因为我们可以用一直在用的LAMBDA
because some of the lambda that I've been playing with.
但是有它们总归方便点儿
But it's nice to have them.
我在这儿略施魔法
So here we're going to do some magic
但不会去解释
which I'm not going to explain.
转到机器语言 执行APPLY-PRIMOP
Go to machine language, apply primop.
加法是在这里运算的
Here's how it adds.
执行加法指令
Execute an add instruction.
然而一门语言有趣的部分
However, the interesting part of a language
在于组合基本元素的粘合剂
is the glue by which the primitives are glued together.
我们接着往下看
So let's look at that.
另一种可能就是
Well, the other possibility
这个复合对象是求值LAMBDA表达式得到的
this is a compound made up by executing a lambda expression,
这是个复合过程
this is a compound procedure.
检测它的类型标志
Well, we'll check its type.
如果是'CLOSURE
If it is closure,
如果是的话 我就得求值这个过程的体
if it's one of those, then I have to do an eval of the body.
过程的体的求值方式则是
The way I do this, the way I deal with this at all
我求值过程的应用是通过
is the way I evaluate the application of a procedure to its arguments,
先扩充程序的求值环境
is by evaluating the body of the procedure
在这个环境中 把过程的形式参数
in the environment resulting from extending the environment of the procedure
跟传递过来的实际参数绑定在一起
with the bindings of the formal parameters
在这个环境中求值过程的体
of the procedure to the arguments that were passed to it.
这句话很长
That was a long sentence.
但其实简单
Well that's easy enough.
一会儿可能会出现许多CAR CDR...
Now here's going to be a lot of CAR-CDRing.
现在我先要得到过程体
I have to get the body of the procedure.
如何取出过程体呢？
Where's the body of the procedure in here?
这里是CAR部分
Well here's the CAR,
这一块是剩下部分的CDR部分
here's the CDR is the whole rest of this.
因此这就是CADR
So here's the CADR.
所以这里我得到的过程体
And so I see, what I have here is the body
是过程对象第二个元素的第二个元素
is the second element of the second element of the procedure.
因此CADR的CADR 也就是CADADR
So it's the CADR of the CADR or the CADADR.
这里取过程对象的CADADR部分
It's the C-A-D-A-D-R, CADADR of the procedure.
为了求值过程体
To evaluate the body
要在参数绑定后的新环境之中进行
in the result of binding that's making up more environment,
我还得获取过程的形式参数
well I need the formal parameters of the of the procedure,
要怎么取呢？
what is that?
就是CADR部分的CAR部分
That's the CAR of the CADR.
这很糟糕不是吗？
OK? It's horrible isn't it?
过程的CADR部分
--of the procedure.
在随着过程一起传递过来的环境中
Bind that to the arguments that were passed in the environment,
把形参和由环境传递过来的实参绑定起来
which is passed also as part of the procedure.
也就是CDR的CDR的CAR
Well, that's the CAR of the CDR of the CDR of this,
也就是过程的CADDR部分
CADDR, of the procedure.
（闭合括号中）
Bind, eval, pair, COND, lamda, define--
当然 如果我非常追求整洁
Now, of course, if I were being really a neat character,
并且又非常谨慎
and I was being very careful,
我会在后面多加一个情况
I would actually put an extra case here
来判断是否出错
for checking for certain errors like,
比如应用在参数上的是一个过程吗？
did you try to apply one to an argument?
如果不是 这里就是未定义的过程类型
You get a undefined procedure type.
我在这里也会这么做
So I may as well do that anyway.
像这样 在ELSE子句中返回错误
--else, some sort of error, like that.
当然 在现实中的一些系统中
Now, of course, again, in some sort of more real system,
出于专业设计的考虑
written for professional reasons,
这里可能会根据某种分派
this would be written with a case analysis
来进行“分情况处理”
done by some sort of dispatch.
回到这里 我可能还会添加新的条件来检查
Over here, I would probably have other cases
比如 这是编译过的代码吗？
like, is this compiled code?
这很重要
It's very important.
这样的话我就可以区分
I might have distinguished the kind of code
过程是直接由解释LAMBDA表达式而来
that's produced by a directly evaluating a lambda in interpretation
还是从另外的编译器中得到的 等等
from code that was produced by somebody's compiler or something like that.
之后再讨论这个话题
And we'll talk about that later.
又或许是 我必须要执行的一段Frotran代码
Or is this a piece Fortran program I have to go off and execute.
这完全是可能的
It's a perfectly possible thing, at this point, to do that.
实际上 我用具体语法写的这个求值器
In fact, in this concrete syntax evaluator I'm writing here,
假定了它是用Lisp来编写的
there's an assumption built in that this is Lisp,
这是因为我用了CAR和CDR
because I'm using CARs and CDRs.
用CAR来取运算符
CAR means the operator,
用CDR来取运算对象
and CDR means the operand.
教科书上给出了一个用抽象语法编写的求值器
In the text, there is an abstract syntax evaluator
它使用的都是抽象的名字
which these could be-- these are given abstract names
比如OPERATOR、OPERAND
like operator, and operand,
以及类似的名字
and all these other things are like that.
那样的话
And, in that case,
你可以毫无问题地用ALGOL来重新实现
you could reprogram it to be ALGOL with no problem.
写完APPLY之后
Well, here we have added another couple of things
又有一些东西没有定义
that we haven't defined.
我先不操心这两个
I don't think I'll worry about these at all,
我们稍后讨论这个很重要的BIND
however, this one will be interesting later.
现在我们来快速过一遍 结束这一部分
Let's just proceed through this and get it done.
只剩下两块黑板了 不能够写太长
There's only two more blackboards so it can't be very long.
我还得悉心裁剪才能刚好写下
It's carefully tailored to exactly fit.
嗯 还剩下点什么？
Well, what do we have left?
我们得定义这里的EVLIST
We have to define EVLIST, which is over here.
EVLIST只不过是
And EVLIST is nothing more
在运算对象上映射某个函数得到参数
than a map down a bunch of operands producing arguments.
但是我还是要写出来看看
But I'm going to write it out.
我把它写出来的原因有点神秘
And one of the reasons I'm going to write this out is for a mystical reason,
我想让这个求值器简单得
which is I want to make this evaluator so simple
可以求值自身
that it can understand itself.
我真的很在意这一点
I'm going to really worry about that a little bit.
现在我就把它完全写在这里
So let's write it out completely.
我并不关心
See, I don't want to worry about
它能否把过程作为参数传递
whether or not the thing can pass functional arguments.
求值器并不会用到这些参数
The value evaluator is not going to use them.
求值器也不会生成一个是过程的值
The evaluator is not going to produce functional values.
因此 如果另外有个不同的语言
So even if there were a different, alternative language
跟这个又非常相似
that were very close to this,
这个求值器能够求值像Scheme这样的复杂语言
this evaluates a complex language like Scheme
Scheme是能够把过程当做参数传递的
which does allow procedural arguments, procedural values, and procedural data.
但当我在求值ALGOL时
But even if I were evaluating ALGOL,
尽管ALGOL并不支持过程值
which doesn't allow procedural values,
这个求值器也能正常工作
I could use this evaluator.
因为这个解释器 并没有对这个做过什么假定
And this evaluator is not making any assumptions about that.
实际上 就算这个求值器
And, in fact, if this evaluator were to be restricted
被限制不允许那么做 也没有什么关系
to not being able to that, it wouldn't matter
因为它没有使用那些高级功能
because it doesn't use any of those clever things.
这就是我为什么要把它设计得非常简单
So that's why I'm arranging this to be super simple.
这几乎是所有可能的语言求值器的核心
This is sort of the kernel of all possible language evaluators.
回到这个定义上来
How about that?
EVLIST -- 它是什么呢？
Evlist--  well, what is it?
这个过程接收两个参数 L和ENV
It's the procedure of two arguments, l and an environment,
其中L是个表
where l is a list
这样的话 如果参数表是空表
such that if the list of arguments is the empty list,
那么结果就是空表
then the result is the empty list.
否则的话 我就要组合
Otherwise, I want to cons up
在ENV中求值运算对象表的CAR部分
result of evaluating the CAR of the
在ENV中求值运算对象CAR部分的结果
the CAR of the list of operands in the environment.
我想先求值第一个运算对象
So I want the first operand evaluated,
返回的结果将是一个新表
and I'm going to make a list of the results
是通过把这个和
by CONSing that onto the result
用CDR递归EVLIST的结果组合得到的
of this EVLISTing as a CDR recursion,
在同样的ENV下 L的CDR部分
the CDR of the list relative to the same environment.
（闭合括号中）
Evlist, cons, else, COND, lambda, define--
还有一个过程
OK? And I have one more
我也想写在这里
that I want to put on the blackboard.
它是这整个的关键
It's the essence of this whole thing.
还要深入一个层次
And there's some sort of next layer down.
也就是COND语句
Conditionals--
在剩下的东西中
conditionals are the only thing left
EVCOND是唯一的重要过程
that are sort of substantial.
解决完这个后
Then below that, we have to worry about
我们再讨论LOOKUP和BIND
things like lookup and bind,
稍后再来讨论
and we'll look at that in a second.
在这个层次上 这是非常重要的
But of the substantial stuff at this level of detail,
下一个重要的事就是如何处理COND语句
next important thing is how you deal with conditionals.
那么 我们怎么来处理呢？
Well, how do we have a conditional thing?
它是一个过程
It's a procedure
参数是一组子句CLAUSES和环境ENV
of clauses and an environment.
它做些什么呢？
And what does it do?
如果子句为空
It says, if I've no more clauses,
我得有一个返回值
well, I have to give this a value.
可能是一个错误
It could be that it was an error.
如果遍历完了所有条件 都没有符合的
Supposing it run off the end of a conditional,
那么它可能有任意的行为
it's pretty arbitrary.
这完全取决于程序员要怎么处理
It's up to me as programmer to choose what I want to happen.
现在对我来说最方便的是
It's convenient for me, right now, to write down
让它返回一个空表
this has a value which is the empty list,
这无所谓
doesn't matter.
为了检查出错误
For error checking,
有些人喜欢在这里写点别的
some people might prefer something else.
下面的更有意思
But the interesting things are the following ones.
如果我遇到了ELSE子句
If I've got an else clause--
请看 我们有一个由子句组成的表
You see, if I have a list of clauses,
其中每个子句也是一个表
then each clause is a list.
因此谓词就应该是CLAUSES的CAAR部分
And so the predicate part is the CAAR of the clauses.
它是
It's the CAR,
CLAUSES表中第一个元素的CAR部分
which is the first part of the first clause in the list of clauses.
如果它是'ELSE的话
If it's an else,
就意味着整个COND表达式的结果
then it means I want my result of the conditional
就是求值匹配表达式的结果
to be the result of evaluating the matching expression.
所以我求值CADAR部分
So I eval the CADAR.
这是第一个子句的
So this is the first clause,
第二个元素 也就是CADAR
the second element of it, CADAR--
也就是CLAUSES的CAR部分的CADR部分
CADR of a CAR-- of the clauses,
求值的环境是ENV
with respect to the environment.
下一种可能性更有意思
Now the next possibility is more interesting.
如果它返回FALSE的话
If it's false,
如果谓词表中的第一个谓词
if the first predicate in the predicate list
既不是ELSE子句 又不为FALSE
is not an else, and it's not false,
也就是它不是保留字ELSE
if it's not the word else,
并且也不是一个值为FALSE的东西
and if it's not a false thing--
如果为FALSE又要怎么处理呢？
Let's write down what it is if it's a false thing.
如果在相应的环境中
If the result of evaluating the first clause -- first predicate,
求值子句中第一个谓词的结果
the clauses--  respect the environment,
如果求值的结果是FALSE的话
if that evaluation yields false,
这就意味着 还得接着判断后面的子句
then it means, I want to look at the next clause.
第一个就扔掉不管了
So I want to discard the first one.
所以就进入下一个EVCOND循环
So we just go around loop, evcond,
在对应的环境中继续判断子句的CDR部分
the CDR of the clauses relative to that environment.
又或者 我遇到了求值为TRUE的子句
And otherwise, I had a true clause,
这样的话 我想在对应的环境中
what I want is to evaluate
求值CLAUSES的CADAR部分
the CADAR of the clauses relative to that environment.
快了 快完成了
Boy, it's almost done.
基本上完整了
It's quite close to done.
把这一部分结束
I think we're going to finish this part off.
再回顾一下这个求值器
So just buzzing through this evaluator,
它基本上就是这样了
but so far you're seeing almost everything.
接着来看一张幻灯片
Let's look at the next transparency here.
这是BIND的定义
And see IS, Here is bind.
BIND用于在环境中添加新的绑定
Bind is for making more table.
我们要在这里
And what we are going to do here is make a--
为环境结构创建一个新框架
we're going to make a new frame for an environment structure.
环境结构是通过由框架组成的表
The environment structure is going to be represented
来表示的
as a list of frames.
给定一个已有的环境
So given an existing environment structure,
我可以通过把一个新建的框架
I'm going to make a new environment structure
CONS在已有的环境上
by consing a new frame
来获得新的环境
onto the existing environment structure,
正在应用的过程中 那些被绑定变量
where the new frame consists of the result of pairing up the variables,
与传递给过程的参数值结合在一起
which are the bound variables of the procedure I'm applying,
组成了我们所创建的新框架
to the values which are the arguments that were passed that procedure.
BIND其实就是创建表
This is just making a list,
环境就是一组由框架组成的表
adding a new element to our list of frames,
把新的元素加入其中
which is an environment structure,
也就形成了新的环境
to make a new environment.
而PAIR-UP的定义非常简单
Where pair-up is very simple.
PAIR-UP只不过是
Pair-up is nothing more
如果我们有一个变量表和一个值表
than if I have a list of variables and a list of values,
那么 如果它俩的元素个数又相同
well, if I run out of variables and if I run out of values,
就可以让它们一一对应
everything's OK.
否则的话 就是参数传递多了
Otherwise, I've given too many arguments.
如果值的个数比变量的个数多
If I've not run out of variables, but I've run out of values,
那就说明参数传递少了
that I have too few arguments.
通常的情况是
And in the general case,
如果没有出错 又没有完成的话
where I don't have any errors, and I'm not done,
我就添加一个由第一个变量
OK? Then I really am just adding a new pair
和第一个参数组成的新序对
of the first variable with the first argument,
这是第一个值
the first value,
把它们CONS在
onto a list resulting from pairing-up
剩余变量和值组成的表上
the rest of the variables with the rest of the values.
LOOKUP也同样简单
Lookup is of course equally simple.
加入我要在环境中查找一个符号
If I have to look up a symbol in an environment,
那么 如果是空环境
well, if the environment is empty,
那么就说明 该变量尚未绑定
then I've got an unbound variable.
否则
Otherwise,
我就要使用一个特殊的关联表查找过程
what I'm going to do is use a special pair list lookup procedure,
我们不久就会看到它的定义
which we'll have very shortly,
用它在环境的第一个框架中查找该符号
of the symbol in the first frame of the environment.
由于我知道这个环境不是空的
Since I know the environment is not empty,
因此 它至少有一个框架
it must have a first frame.
所以 我就在它第一个框架中查找
So I lookup the symbol in the first frame.
找到的序对会传递给这里的VCELL
That becomes the value cell here.
如果VCELL为空
OK? And then, if the value cell is empty,
那就说明当前框架中没有这个符号
if there is no such value cell,
我就需要在环境中剩下的框架中查找
then I have to continue and look at the rest of the frames.
VCELL为空 意味着当前框架没有相应的符号
It means there was nothing found there.
如果没有找到
So that's a property of ASSQ is it returns emptiness
ASSQ就会返回空表
if it doesn't find something.
如果找到了
but if it did find something,
那么我就使用VCELL的CDR部分
then I'm going to use the CDR of the value cell here,
因为VCELL是变量和值组成的序对
which is the thing that was the pair consisting of the variable and the value.
因此可以用CDR取得对应的值
So the CDR of it is the value part. OK?
ASSQ这个过程你们之前见过
Finally, ASSQ is something you've probably seen already.
ASSQ的参数是一个符号和一个由序对组成的表
ASSQ takes a symbol and a list of pairs,
如果表为空 它就返回空表
and if the list is empty, it's empty.
如果这个符号是ALIST的第一个元素
If the symbol is the first thing in the list--
这里写错了
That's an error.
应该是CAAR
That should be CAAR, C-A-A-R.
大家注意一下
Everybody note that.
就是这里 看到了吗？
Right there, OK?
总之
And in any case,
如果符号等于表的CAAR
f the symbol is the CAAR of the A list,
那么我就返回ALIST中第一个序对
then I want the first, the first pair, in the alist.
换句话说 这个键匹配了正确的条目
So, in other words, if this is the key matching the right entry,
否则的话
otherwise,
我就需要在剩下的表中继续查找
I want to look up that symbol in the rest.
这里有个笔误 很抱歉
Sorry for producing a bug, bugs appear.
好了 不管如何
Well, in any case,
你们基本上已经看到了全貌
you're pretty much seeing the whole thing now.
虽然我们的代码风格非常丑陋
It's a very beautiful thing,
但是作为所有语言的核心
even though it's written in an ugly style,
它却是非常美妙
being the kernel of every language.
我提议 让我们再欣赏一会儿
I suggest that we just-- let's look at it for a while.
[音乐]
[ALSO SPRACH ZARATHUSTRA]
大家有什么问题吗？
Are there any questions?
没有的话就休息一会儿吧
Alright, I suppose it's time to take a small break then.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
元循环求值器 I
现在 我们将用一个实例
OK, now we're just going to do a little bit of practice
来理解一下求值器的运作过程
understanding what it is we've just shown you. OK?
我们通过手工进行代换
What we're going to do is go through, in detail,
来深入解释器的详细工作原理
an evaluation by informally substituting through the interpreter.
由于我们的求值器不支持赋值和定义
And since we have no assignments or definitions in this interpreter,
我们也就不用担心副作用
we have no possible side effects,
因此我们可以放心大胆地进行代换
and so the we can do substitution with impunity
不用担心任何副作用
and not worry about results.
我们将要尝试去手工代换
So the particular problem I'd like to look at
这个复杂的表达式
is it an interesting one.
(EVAL
It's the evaluation of
'(((LAMBDA (X) (LAMBDA (Y) (+ X Y)))
quote, open, open, open, lambda of x, lambda of y plus x y,
（闭合括号中）
lambda, lambda,
要把它应用在3和4上
applied to three, applied to four,
求值过程是发生在全局环境E0中的
in some global environment which I'll call e0.
这里的这个表达式
So what we have here
是个参数为X的一元过程
is a procedure of one argument x,
返回一个参数为Y的一元过程
which produces as its value a procedure of one argument y,
后者计算X+Y
which adds x to y.
外层的这个过程应用于数字3
We are applying the procedure of one argument x to three.
所以X应该是3
So x should become three.
返回的结果是一个参数为Y的一元过程
And the result of that should be procedure of one argument y,
该过程将应用于数字4
which will then apply to 4.
然后要做的也很简单
And there is a very simple case,
计算X+Y即可
they will then add those results.
具体做之前
And now in order to do that,
先来构造一个非常简单的环境模型
I want to make a very simple environment model.
到了现在 我相信你们已经想到
And at this point, you should already have in your mind
这个过程产生的环境了
the environments that this produces.
我们从全局环境开始
But we're going to start out with a global environment,
我们把它记作E0
which I'll call e0,
就像这样
which is that.
里面应该有过程+、*的定义
And it's going to have in it things, definitions for plus, and times,
这里 我们用希腊字母来表示过程对象 这样有趣点
and-- using Greek letters, isn't that interesting, for the objects--
-、/、CAR、CDR、CONS以及EQ?
and minus, and quotient, and CAR, and CDR, and CONS, and EQ,
其它需要的基本过程都在全局环境中
and everything else you might imagine in a global environment.
每个符号都对应着一个过程对象
It's got something there for each of those things,
这些都是解释器自带的
something the machine is born with,
这就是E0
that's e0.
现在 这个求值要怎样进行呢？
Now what does it mean to do this evaluation?
我们来看看这些特殊形式
Well, we go through the set of special forms.
首先 这不是数字
First of all, this is not a number.
也不是符号
This is not a symbol.
这不是一个引用表达式
Gee, it's not a quoted expression.
虽然外层是一个引用表达式
This is a quoted expression,
但并不是我想要去求值的那个
but that's not what I mentioned.
我想问的是
The question is,
被引用的这个表达式 是否也是个引用表达式？
whether or not the thing which is quoted is quoted expression?
我是在求值一个表达式
I'm evaluating an expression.
这个引号是为了引用这个特定表达式
This just says it's this particular expression.
而被引用的并非引用表达式
This is not a quoted expression.
当然 它也不是以LAMBDA开头
OK? It's not a thing that begins with lambda.
也不以COND开头
It's not a thing that begins with COND.
因此它是过程的应用
Therefore, it's an application of its of an operated operands.
这是一个组合式
It's a combination.
既然它是组合式
The combination thus has
这就是它的运算符
this as the operator
而这是它的运算对象
and this is the operands.
这就意味着 我要
Well, that means that what I'm going to do is
把它转换成
transform this into apply of eval,
(APPLY (EVAL '((LAMBDA (X) (LAMBDA (y)
of quote, open, open lambda of x, lambda of y--
也就是在E0环境中
I'm evaluating the operator--
求值(+ X Y)
plus x y, in the environment,
不要漏了
also e0,
要应用到的运算对象则是
with the operands that I'm going to apply this to,
用EVLIST求值参数的结果
the arguments being the result of EVLIST,
也就是'(4)
the list containing four, fin e0.
我用这个特殊的记号来表示
I'm using this funny notation here for e0
这是为了指代那个环境
because this should be that environment.
我无法为它命名
I haven't a name for it,
因为我没有环境来存放的名字
because I have no environment to name it in.
你当然可以把看作是
So this is just a representation
某种引用表达式
what would be a quoted expression, if you will.
在那里 它表示环境这种数据结构
The data structure, which is the environment, goes there.
好的 这是变换后的结果
Well, that's what we're seeing here.
为了执行这个表达式
Well in order to do this,
我还得求值这两个表达式
I have to do this, and I have to do that.
EVLIST简单点
Well this one's easy,
我们先计算这个吧
so why don't we do that one first. OK?
这就被归约为
This turns into apply of eval--
上面的某些部分直接抄过来就好
just copying something now.
代换的过程中少不了照抄
Most of the substitution rule is copying.
抄写的时候我就不多加解释了
So I'm going to not say the words when I copy,
这样能快一点儿
because it's faster.
EVLIST的部分就代换成为
And then the EVLIST is going to turn into a
(CONS (EVAL '4 )
cons, of eval, of four, in e0--
因为它不是空表
because it was not an empty list--
(EVLIST '() ))
onto the result of EVLISTing, on the empty list, in e0.
我要省略一些步骤了
And I'm going to start leaving out steps soon,
因为太详细就有些无聊了
because it's going to get boring.
下一步跟上面基本上一样
But this is basically the same thing as apply, of eval--
继续照抄
I'm going to keep doing this--
(((LAMBDA (X) (LAMBDA (Y) (+ X Y)) 3) 4) )
the lambda of x, the lambda of y, plus xy, 3, close, e0.
看来我还宝刀未老嘛
I'm a pretty good machine.
下面对4求值
Well, eval of four,
4是一个数字
that's meets the question, is it a number.
结果就应该是(CONS 4
So that's cons, right, cons of 4.
EVLIST对空表求值 结果也是空表
And EVLIST of the empty list is the empty list,
也就是这个
so that's this.
这个非常容易理解
OK. And that's very simple to understand,
就是一个只含有4的表
because that means the list containing four itself.
继续代换为 (APPLY (EVAL
So this is nothing more than apply of eval,
'((LAMBDA (X) (LAMBDA (Y) (+ X Y))
quote, open, open, lambda of x, lambda of y, plus x y,
3) 4) )
three applied to, e0, applied to the list four--
应用在'(4)上 这样就完成了
applied to the list four-- bang
这是这一步的结果
So that's that step.
现在让我们进行下一步 更有意思的一步
Now let's look at the next, more interesting thing.
这行代码要如何求值？
What do I do to evaluate that?
为了求值这一部分
Evaluating this means
我得先求值-- 首先 它不是--
means I have to evaluate-- Well, it's not.
这是一个应用
It's nothing but an application.
它并不是特殊形式
It's not one of the special things.
如果应用中的运算符
If the application of this operator,
就是这里
which we see here--
这就是运算符
here's the operator--
应用在这个运算对象上
applied to this operands,
形成了一个组合式
that combination.
现在我们要如何来求值呢？
But we know how to do that,
它是COND语句中的最后一种情况
because that's the last case of the conditional.
在这步求值中 进行的代换是
So substituting in for this evaluation,
把运算符的求值结果
it's apply of eval of the operator
应用在EVLIST的运算对象上
in the EVLIST of the operands.
这也就是 (APPLY (APPLY (EVAL
Well, it's apply, of apply, of eval,
'(LAMBDA (X) (LAMBDA (Y) (+ X Y)))
of quote, open, lambda of x, lambda of y, plus x y,
（闭合括号中）
lambda, lambda,
)
in environment e0.
我就直接给出运算对象的求值结果了
I'm going to short circuit the evaluation of the operands,
具体过程跟之前是一样的
because they're the same as they were before.
我有一个表'(3)
I got a list containing three,
把它应用于'(4)
apply that, and apply that to four.
我们接着看
Well let's see.
对一个LAMBDA表达式求值
Eval of a lambda expression
会产生一个过程对象
produces a procedure object.
继续变换就是 (APPLY (APPLY
So this is apply, of apply,
然后是一个过程对象 '(CLOSURE
of the procedure object closure,
它里面包含了过程的体
which contains the body of the procedure, x,
它绑定了变量X
which is lambda, which binds x [UNINTELLIGIBLE]
然后是函数体内部
the internals of the body,
它返回一个参数为Y的单参过程
it returns the procedure of one argument y,
这个过程计算X+Y
which adds x to y.
这个过程对象捕获了环境
Environment e0 is now captured in it,
因为这些求值都是在中发生的
because this was evaluated with respect to e0.
现在 也是CLOSURE对象的一部分
e0 is part now of the closure object.
先应用于'(3)
Apply that to open, three, close, apply,
再应用于'(4)
to open, 4, close, apply.
在这步到这步的过程中
So going from this step to this step
我构建了一个过程对象
meant that I made up a procedure object
它捕获了
which captured in it
并将其作为本身的一部分
e0 as part of the procedure object.
现在 要把它们传递给APPLY了
Now, we're going to pass those to apply.
我们得把这个过程
We have to apply this procedure
应用在对应的参数上
to that set of arguments.
这里的过程并不是基本过程
Well, but that procedure is not primitive.
它有一个类型标志'CLOSURE
It's, in fact, a thing which has got the tag closure,
因此还需要进行参数绑定
and, therefore, what we have to do is do a bind.
必须要绑定
We have to bind.
在这里构造的新环境
A new environment is made at this point,
它有一个父环境
which has as its parent environment
父环境是这里的
the one over here, e0, that environment.
我们把新环境记作
And we'll call this one, e1.
这里要绑定些什么呢？
Now what's bound in there?
变量X绑定为值3
x is bound to three.
这里写X=3
So I have x equal three.
就是这些
That's what's in there.
新环境记作E1
And we'll call that e1.
而这个表达式会变换为
So what this transforms into
对一个过程体的求值
is an eval of the body
就是这个 在这里
of this, which is this,
这个过程的体
the body of that procedure,
在刚才创建的中进行求值
in the environment that you just saw.
也就是 (APPLY (EVAL
So that's an apply, of eval,
'(LAMBDA (Y) (+ X Y)) )
quote, open, lambda of y, plus x y-- the body-- in e1.
把求值的结果应用于4
And apply the result of that to four,
也就是'(4)
open, close, 4-- list of arguments.
到了这里就很清晰了
Well, that's sensible enough
我知道该如何求值LAMBDA表达式
because evaluating a lambda, I know what to do.
也就是(APPLY
That means I apply,
一个过程对象'(CLOSURE
the procedure which is closure,
它绑定参数Y 计算X+Y
binds one argument y, adds x to y,
并且捕获了环境
with e1 captured in it.
你应该已经见过了 对吧？
And you should really see this. Right?
我构造了一个CLOSURE对象
I somehow manufactured a closure.
放在这里
I should've put this here.
之前的那个也是
There was one over here too.
这是现在的这个
OK? Well, there's one here now.
它捕获了环境
I've captured e1,
而这个是参数为Y的一元过程
and this is the procedure of one argument y,
先不管它具体是什么
whatever this is.
我们只知道它是一个CLOSURE
That's what that is there, that closure.
将这个过程应用于'(4)
OK? I'm going to apply that to four.
很简单
OK. Well, that's easy enough.
我需要通过复制一个指针
That means I have to make a new environment
就是这个过程的指针
by copying this pointer,
来构造一个新环境
which was the pointer of the procedure,
同时还得把参数Y跟值4绑定
which binds y equal 4 with that environment.
我把这个新环境 记作
And here's my new environment, which I'll call e2.
当然 这里的这个应用
And, of course, this application then
其过程体的求值 是在中进行的
is evaluate the body in e2.
所以这就变成了对过程体的求值
So this is eval, the body,
也就是 (EVAL '(+ X Y) )
which is plus x y, in the environment e2.
但由于这是一个应用
But this is an application,
所以又代换为 (APPLY (EVAL '+ )
so this is the apply, of eval, plus in e2,
(EVLIST '(X Y) ))
an EVLIST, quote, open, x y, in e2.
我们来看
Well, but let's see.
下一步代换为 (APPLY
That is apply, the object
求值‘+得到的结果
which is a result of that and plus.
所以我们从开始找
So here we are in e2,
'+既不在 也不在
plus is not here, it's not here,
‘+是中的基本运算符
yes, but's here as some primitive operator.
这个基本运算符是用于加法的
So it's the primitive operator for addition.
把它应用于 在中求值X和Y的结果
Apply that to the result of evaluating x and y in e2.
我们知道X是3 Y是4
But we can see that x is three and y is four.
所以这里是'(3 4)
So that's a three and four, here.
然后就神奇地得到结果7
And that magically produces for me a seven.
我再来整理一下这个过程 这样你们
I wanted to go through this so you would see,
就能了解这其中的重要本质
essentially, one important ingredient,
这个过程中传递了些什么？
which is what's being passed around,
每个模块持有什么 又负责什么？
and who owns what, and what his job is.
有哪些模块呢？
So what do we have here?
一个是EVAL
We have eval,
还有个APPLY
We have eval, and we have apply,
两个主要角色
the two main players.
它们之间有个像这样的大循环
And there is a big loop the goes around like this.
其中 EVAL为APPLY生成过程和参数
Which is eval produces a procedure and arguments for apply.
也有些事情 EVAL也可以自己做
Now some things eval could do by itself.
都是一些细小的事情
Those are little self things here.
并不十分有趣
They're not interesting.
同时 EVAL也逐个求值所有的参数
Also eval evaluates all of the arguments, one after another.
也没什么意思
That's not very interesting.
APPLY可以应用像+这类的过程
Apply can apply some procedures like plus,
这很普通
not very interesting.
然而 如果APPLY不能应用像+这样的过程
However, if apply can't apply a procedure like plus,
它就为EVAL生成一个表达式及相应的环境
it produces an expression and environment for eval.
过程的参数封装了
The procedural arguments wrap up
计算所必需的状态
essentially the state of a computation
以及相应的环境
and, certainly, the expression of environment.
但我们接下来要做的
And so what we're actually going to do next
并不是完整的状态
is not the complete state,
因为它没有说明谁需要返回的结果
because it doesn't say who wants the answers.
我们要做的就是
But what we're going to do--
总是把某个表达式以及相应的环境
it's always got something like an expression of environment
或者过程对象以及其参数
or procedure and arguments
在这个循环之间不断传递
as the main loop that we're going around.
这里还有一些小型的子循环 比如EVLIST
There are minor little sub loops like eval through EVLIST,
又或者是EVAL中的EVCOND循环
or eval through evcond,
甚至于APPLY调用PRIMITIVE-APPLY
or apply through a primitive apply.
但是它们并不是最主要的
But they're not the essential things.
这整个就是我想让你们看到的
So that's what I wanted you to see.
有什么问题吗？
Are there any questions?
David 请说
Yes. David
学生：我不明白为什么X是3
AUDIENCE: I'm trying to understand how x got down to three
而不是4
instead of four.
在那个部分
At the early part of the--
教授：是在这里
PROFESSOR: Here.
你想知道X是如何跟3绑定的
You want to know how x got down to three?
学生：因为X是外层过程的参数
AUDIENCE: Because x is the outer procedure,
而内层过程中既有X又有Y
and x and y are the inner procedure.
教授：明白了
PROFESSOR: Fine.
代换的过程中 我已经非常小心了
Well, I was very careful and mechanical.
或许首先 我应该把这些过程
First of all, I should write those procedures
重新编排得更易读一点
again for you, pretty printed.
你之所以有所疑惑
First order of business,
或许是因为你把程序看岔了
because you're probably not reading them well.
所以这里应该是
So I have here
一个以X为参数的过程
that procedure of-- was it x over there--
它返回一个以Y为参数的过程
which is -- value of that procedure of y
后者计算X+Y
which adds x to y,
（闭合括号中）
lambda, lambda,
外面的过程应用到3上
applied that to three,
把得到的结果应用到4上
takes the result of that, and applied that to four.
这个和之前那个是一样的 对吧？
Is that not what I wrote? OK?
现在 你可以立马发现
Now, you should immediately see that
这里是一个应用
here is an application--
我先换根白粉笔
let me get a white piece of chalk--
这一部分是应用 是一个组合式
here is an application, a combination.
这部分是组合式的运算符
OK? That combination has this as the operator
而这是运算对象
and this as the operand.
这个3会跟这里的X绑定
The three is going in for the x here.
而这个组合式的结果
The result of this
是一个参数为Y的一元过程
is a procedure of one argument y,
它将应用于4
which gets applied to four.
明白了吧？
OK?
所以你可能只是看岔了
So you just weren't reading the expression right.
而你们在这里看到的
The way you see that over here. OK.
是一个实际的过程对象 它有一个参数X
is that here I have the actual procedure object, x.
这个CLOSURE将应用于3
It's getting applied to three,
也就是'(3)
the list containing three.
得到的结果再应用于'(4)
What I'm left over with is something which gets applied to four.
还有疑问吗？
Are there any other questions?
那就休息一下吧
Time for our next small break then.
谢谢大家
Thank you.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
元循环求值器 I
教授：课上到这里
PROFESSOR: Let's see, at this point,
你们可能开始觉得
you should be getting the feeling,
Sussman教授又在胡说八道些什么
what's this nonsense this Sussman character is feeding me?
他讲的东西奇怪、愚蠢又毫无意义
There's an awful lot of strange nonsense here.
他还宣称要给我们解释Lisp
After all, he purported to explain to me Lisp,
然后在黑板上给我们写了一个Lisp程序
and he wrote me a Lisp program on the blackboard.
他还说：“这个Lisp程序就是Lisp解释器”
The Lisp program was intended to be interpreted for Lisp,
但是为了运行这个Lisp程序
but you need a Lisp interpreter
你还先得有一个Lisp解释器啊
in order to understand that program.
那个程序怎么能告诉我
How could that program have told me anything
有关于Lisp的知识呢？
there is to be known about Lisp?
它为什么又不是空中楼阁呢？
How is that not completely vacuous?
这件事非常奇怪
It's a very strange thing.
它究竟告诉了我什么？
Does it tell me anything at all?
我们发现 其实这整件事
Well, you see, the whole thing
非常像我们在这张幻灯片上看到的
is sort of like these Escher's hands
Escher所画的手
that we see on this slide.
是的 EVAL和APPLY
Yes, eval and apply
彼此画出彼此
each sort of draw each other
并且构造出了真实的东西
and construct the real thing,
它完全是自己画出了自己
which can sit out and draw itself.
Escher真是绝顶聪明
Escher was a very brilliant man,
他只不过叫不出这些精灵的名字
he just didn't know the names of these spirits.
我现在要做的就是
Well, I'm going to do now,
使你们相信
is I'm going to try to convince you
这一切都是有意义的
that both this mean something,
并且
and, as a aside,
我将要解释为什么我们不需要DEFINE
I'm going to show you why you don't need definitions.
事实证明 我们并不需要DEFINE
Just turns out that sort of falls out,
为了进行数学意义上的计算
why definitions are not essential in a mathematical sense
DEFINE并不是必需的
for doing all the things we need to do for computing.
我们来看一下
Well, let's see here.
考虑下面的一小段程序
Consider the following small program,
它有什么作用？
what does it mean?
这是一个计算指数的程序
This is a program for computing exponentials.
EXPT计算X的N次方
The exponential of x to the nth power is if--
如果N为0
n is zero,
那么结果就是1
then the result is one.
否则
Otherwise,
结果就是X乘以
I want the product of x
(EXPT X (- N 1))))
and the result of exponentiating x to the n minus one power.
应该没错
I think I got it right.
一个递归定义
Now this is a recursive definition.
用EXPT自身
It's a definition of the exponentiation
来定义EXPT过程自己
procedure in terms of itself.
就像我之前说的那样
And, as it has been mentioned before,
你们高中数学老师在教这些东西的时候
your high school geometry teacher
你们一定学得很痛苦
probably gave you a hard time about things like that.
这样定义合理吗？
Was that justified?
为什么这种自引用的定义
Why does this self referential definition
能够说得通呢？
make any sense?
首先我要说的是
Well, first of all, I'm going to convince you that
你们高中数学老师并非在胡说八道
your high school geometry teacher was not telling you nonsense.
考虑下面的几组定义
Consider the following set of definitions here.
X+Y=3
x plus y equals three,
X-Y=1
and x minus y equal one.
这个方程用Y来告诉你X
Well, gee, this tells you x in terms of y,
而这个方程或许是用X来告诉你Y
and this one tells you y in terms of x, presumably.
碰巧这组方程有唯一的解
And yet this happens to have a unique solution in x and y.
然而 我也可能有这样的方程
However, I could also write
2X+2Y=6
two x plus two y is six.
这两个方程有无穷多个解
These two equations have an infinite number solutions.
我还可以有像这样的方程
And I could write you, for example,
X-Y=2
x minus y equal 2,
而下面的这两个方程没有解
and these two equations have no solutions.
这里 我有三组线性方程组
Well, I have here three sets of simultaneous linear equations,
分别是这组、这组和这组
this set, this set, and this set.
它们的解的数目完全不同
But they have different numbers of solutions.
解的数目并不取决于方程的形式
The number of solutions is not in the form of the equations.
三组方程都有一样的形式
They all three sets have the same form.
解的数目取决于方程的内容
The number of solutions is in the content.
我不能通过观察方程的形式
I can't tell by looking at the form of a definition
来判断解的数目
whether it makes sense,
必须要看它的内容
only by its detailed content.
比如 对于线性方程组
What are the coefficients,
它的系数都是什么？
for example, in the case of linear equations?
我不能够通过观察
So I shouldn't expect to be able to tell
像这样的简单情况
looking at something like this,
来判定
from some simple things like,
EXPT就是这个递归方程的解
oh yes, EXPT is the solution of this recursion equation.
我不能说 EXPT就是那个过程
Expt is the procedure
如果我们把它代换入其中
which if substituted in here,
它就能给我们返回EXPT
gives me expt back.
能跟上吗？
OK?
通过观察这个形式 我也无法判别
I can't tell, looking at this form,
EXPT是否有唯一解
whether or not there's a single, unique solution for EXPT,
有无穷个解 还是根本没有解
an infinite number of solutions, or no solutions.
我们要了解它是如何计数的
It's got to be how it counts
或者是一些类似的计算细节
and things like that, the details.
这可比在线性代数难多了
And it's harder in programming than linear algebra.
程序设计中可用的定理并不多
There aren't too many theorems about it in programming.
我想把这些方程稍稍重写一下
Well, I want to rewrite these equations a little bit,
就是这里的方程
these over here.
因为我们要研究的是这种形式的方程
Because what we're investigating is equations like this.
但是我想用我们比较了解的方程
But I want to play a little with equations
来做演示
like this that we understand,
以便于对于这类问题有深入的洞见
just so we get some insight into this kind of question.
我们可以把这里的方程 改写为
We could rewrite our equations here,
这样的一种有趣形式
say these two, the ones that are interesting,
X=3-Y
as x equals three minus y,
Y=X-1
and y equals x minus one.
我们把这种变换叫什么来着？
What do we call this transformation?
这是一个线性变换 记为T
This is a linear transformation, t.
我们这里就得到了一个方程
Then what we're getting here is an equation
= T
x y equals t of x y.
我要去找什么呢？
What am I looking for?
我在找T的不动点
I'm looking for a fixed point of t.
T的不动点就是方程的解
The solution is a fixed point of t.
所以 如果我们能通过找不动点
So the methods we should have for looking for solutions to equations,
来求解方程
if I can do it by fixed points,
这看来是可行的
might be applicable.
如果我可以用不动点
If I have a means of finding a solution
来求解方程
to an equations by fixed points--
当然 也许它不可行
just, might not work--
不过也可以借鉴来
but it might be applicable
研究如何求解这类方程
to investigating solutions of equations like this.
重要的是 我想让你们把它看成一个方程
But what I want you to feel is that this is an equation.
它是一个表达式
It's an expression
其中有不同的变量
with several instances of various names
只不过这些名字还得满足一定的约束
which puts a constraint on the name,
这些名字限定了对应变量的取值
saying what that name could have as its value,
我们不能够随意、机械地代换
rather than some sort of mechanical process of substitution right now.
这就是我尝试求解的方程
This is an equation which I'm going to try to solve.
我们来试试看
Well, let's play around and solve it.
首先我需要写下
First of all, I want to write down
跟T相对应的函数
the function which corresponds to t.
我写下的这个T对应的函数
First I want to write down the function which corresponds to t
它的不动点就是这个方程的解
whose fixed point is the answer to this question.
能明白吗？
OK?
让我们来看下面这个过程F
Well, let's consider the following procedure f.
我说 F计算的是这样一个函数
I claim it computes that function.
F本身是一个参数为G的一元过程
f is that procedure of one argument g,
它返回
which is
一个参数为X和N的过程
that procedure of two arguments x and n.
这个过程的定义是：
Which have the property that
如果N为0
if n is zero,
那么结果就是1
then the result is one,
否则的话
otherwise,
结果就是(* X (G X (- N 1)))
the result is the product of x and g, applied to x, and minus n1.
（闭合括号中）
g, times, else, COND, lambda, lambda--
没问题吧
OK?
这里 F是一个过程
Here f is a procedure,
如果我能解出这个方程
which if I had a solution to that equation,
如果我找到了一个良好的指数过程
if I had a good exponentiation procedure,
我把这个F应用到那个过程上
and I applied f to that procedure,
那么返回的应该也是一个良好的指数过程
then the result would be a good exponentiation procedure.
这是为什么呢？
Because, what does it do?
这是因为
Well, all it is
F假设G是一个良好的指数过程
is exposing g were a good exponentiation procedure,
那么这里就会返回
well then this would produce, as its value,
一个参数为X和N的过程
a procedure to arguments x and n,
其中如果N=0
such that if n were 0,
结果就是1
the result would be one,
这是非常符合定义的
which is certainly true of exponentiation.
否则 就返回X乘以
Otherwise, it will be the result of multiplying x
用给定的指数过程G
by the exponentiation procedure given to me
计算(G X (- N 1))
with x and n minus one as arguments.
因此如果G能够
So if this computed the correct
正确计算X^(N-1)
exponentiation for n minus one,
那么这个表达式就能正确计算X^N
then this would be the correct exponentiation for exponent n,
所以整个就会是一个正确的求指数过程
so this would have been the right exponentiation procedure.
因此 我在这里真正想指出的是
So what I really want to say here is
过程EXPT是函数F的不动点
E-X-P-T is a fixed point of f.
现在我们的问题在于
Now our problem is
不动点可能不止一个
there might be more than one fixed point.
也可能没有不动点
There might be no fixed points.
所以我们必须求出不动点
I have to go hunting for the fixed points.
需要来解这个方程
Got to solve this equation.
求不动点的方法有很多种
Well there are various ways to hunt for fixed points.
本门课程的第一节课
Of course, the one we played with
我们就用余弦函数做了演示
at the beginning of this term worked for cosine.
先把你的计算器调成弧度制
Going to. Go into radians mode on your calculator
然后一直按COS键
and push cosine, and just keep doing it,
最后数字会稳定在0.73、0.74左右
and you get to some number which is about 0.73 or 0.74.
我记不清是哪个了
I can't remember which.
通过迭代一个过程
By iterating a procedure, which has
我们不断迭代
By iterating a function,
想要寻找不动点的函数
whose fixed point I'm searching for,
有时候 它就会收敛在一个点上
it is sometimes the case that that function will converge
这就是不动点
in producing the fixed point.
碰碰运气
I think we luck out in this case,
来试试这种方法
so let's look for it.
来看这张幻灯片
Let's look at this overhead, this slide.
考虑这么一连串的过程
Consider the following sequence of procedures.
这里的E0
e0 over here
这个E0过程什么也不做
the procedure which does nothing at all.
无论你给它传递什么参数
It's the procedure which produces an error
它都会产生ERROR
for any arguments you give it.
基本上没什么用
It's basically useless.
然而 我可以做近似
Well, however, I can make an approximation.
让我们考虑下 指数过程的最差近似
Let's consider it the worst possible approximation to exponentiation,
因为它什么也做不了
because it does nothing.
假设我调用F
Well, supposing I substituted e0
用E0去代换G
for g by calling f,
这里 G就被代换为了E0
as you see over here on e0.
所以在这里就是E0
So you see over here, have e0 there.
那么E1又成了什么呢？
Then gee, what's e1?
如果用E1来计算X^0
e1 is a procedure which exponentiate things
没什么问题
to the 0th power, with no trouble.
它返回的结果是正确的
It gets the right answer,
任何数的0次幂都是1
anything to the zero is one,
然而计算其它次幂就会出错
and it makes an error on anything else.
现在如果我用E1来调用F
Well, now what if I take e1
把G代换为E1 会发生什么？
and substituted it for g by calling f on e1?
这样的话
Oh gosh,
我就会得到这个二元过程
I have here a procedure of two arguments.
想一想 E1这个过程
Now remember e1
只能正确计算X^0
was appropriate for taking exponentiations of 0,
它只能计算0次幂
for raising to the 0 exponent.
所以这里
So here,
如果N为0 结果就是1
if is n is 0, the result is one,
E2的这部分也正确
so this guy is good for that too.
然而 我可以通过把0次幂乘以X
However, I can use something for raising to the 0th power
来计算1次幂
to multiply it by x to raise something to the first power.
所以E2可以正确计算0次幂和1次幂
So e2 is good for both power 0 and 1.
对吧？
OK?
E3的构造过程和E2是类似的
And e3 is constructed from e2 in the same way.
当然 E3具有同样的参数
And e3, of course, by the same argument
能够正确计算0、1、2次幂
is good for powers 0, one, and two.
对吧？
OK?
因此我就不加证明地告诉你结论
And so I will assert for you, without proof,
因为这个证明过程太难了
because the proof is horribly difficult.
这种事情
And that's the sort of thing that
是由人们所谓“指称语义学家”完成的
people called denotational semanticists do.
这个伟大的想法
I suppose it was invented
应该是由Scott和Strachey提出的
This great idea was invented by Scott and Strachey.
他们是非常著名的数学家
Ah, sort of. They're very famous mathematician types
他们发明了这些程序的解释方式
who invented the interpretation for these programs that we have
就是我刚才讲的那些
that I'm talking to you about right now.
他们通过拓扑学的方法证明了
And they proved, by topology
在我们刚才那种情况下
that there is such a fixed point
不动点是存在的
in the cases that we want.
这个结论就是：
But the assertion is
当N趋近于无穷时 EXPT是E(N)的极限
E-X-P-T is limit as n goes to infinity of em.
我们是通过下面这种方式来构造这个极限的
and And that we've constructed this by the following way.
EXPT=(F (F (F (F ....
--is Well, it's f of, f of, f of, f of, f of--
(F 丄)
f applied to anything at all.
它是什么都无所谓
It didn't matter what that was,
因为它总会生成一个错误
because, in fact, this always produces an error.
（闭合括号中）
Applied to this--
这是F无穷嵌套调用
That's by infinite nesting of f's.
现在我们的问题
So now my problem
又变成了如何构造出无穷调用
is to make some infinite things.
我们需要它们
We need some infinite things.
我怎样才能把F
How am I going to nest up an f
嵌套无穷层呢？
an infinite number of times?
我得把它构造出来
I'd better construct this.
好吧 我不知道
Well, I don't know.
到底怎么样构建一个无穷循环呢？
How would I make an infinite loop at all?
我们先来看个非常简单的无穷循环
Let's take a very simple infinite loop,
能想到的最简单的无穷循环
the simplest infinite loop imaginable.
把这样一个参数为X的函数过程
If I were to take that procedure of one argument x
过程体是(X X)
which applies x to x
看到了吧？
OK?
应用在一个参数为X过程上
and apply that to the procedure of one argument x
后者的过程体也是(X X)
which applies x to x,
这就形成了一个无穷循环
then this is an infinite loop.
这个循环之所以是无穷的
The reason why this is an infinite loop is as follows.
是因为
The way I understand this
我用实际参数代换掉
is I substitute the argument
过程体的形式参数
for the formal parameter in the body.
这样做了以后 这里的每个X
But if I do that, I take for each of these x's,
都被代换为了这个
I substitute one of these,
相当于把最初的表达式又复制了一遍
making a copy of the original expression I just started with,
这就是最简单的无穷循环
the simplest infinite loop.
现在 我要介绍一个特殊的运算符
Now I want to tell you about a particular operator
它是通过对这个无穷循环稍作修改而来
which is constructed by a perturbation from this infinite loop.
我把它记作“Y”
I'll call it y.
它的全称是：Curry的矛盾Y组合子
OK y -- This is called Curry's Paradoxical Combinator of y
这是用二十世纪三十年代的逻辑学家
after a fellow by the name of Curry,
Curry的名字来命名的
who was a logician of the 1930s also.
Y组合子是一个参数为f的过程
And if I have a procedure of one argument f,
它的过程体是什么呢？
what's it going to have in it?
它的内部是某种无穷循环
It's going to have a kind of infinite loop in it,
是一个参数为x的过程
which is that procedure of one argument x
它调用(f (x x))
which applies f to x of x,
这个过程应用在一个参数为X的过程上
applied to that procedure of one argument x,
后者调用(f (x x))
which applies f to f of x.
这个是怎么运作的？
Now what's this do?
假设执行(Y F)
Suppose we apply y to F.
这非常简单
OK? Well, that's easy enough.
这里大写的F跟那边的是同一个
That's this capital F over here.
在这里 很简单
Well, the easiest thing to say there
我把F代换到这里来
is, I substitute F for here.
基本上 我就会得到
So that's going to give me, basically--
因为我待会儿要用这个表达式
because then I'm going to substitute this
代换这里的x
for x in here.
这里就是(F
That F of
我还是把这步写出来吧
Let me actually do it in steps,
这样你们就能看得更全面
so you can see it completely.
我会非常小心 好吗？
I'm going to be very careful. OK?
这里是 ((LAMBDA (x)
This is open, open, lambda of x ,
(F (x x))
capital F, x, x,
把它应用到自身 (LAMBDA (x) (F (x x)))
applied to itself, F of x of x.
把这个表达式代换进去
Substituting this for this in here,
就得到
this is
把这个代进去 得到什么呢？
F applied to-- what is it-- substituting this in here
(F (LAMBDA (x) (F (x x)))
open, open, lambda of x, F, of x and x,
应用到
applied to
(LAMBDA (x) (F (x x))))
lambda of x, F of x of x, F,
（闭合括号中）
lambda, pair, F.
哇 这又是什么？
Oh, but what is this?
我刚才计算的这一部分
This thing over here that I just computed,
就是这里的这部分
is this thing over here.
只不过它被包在另一个F里面
But I just wrapped another F around it.
因此 通过把Y应用在F上
So by applying y to F,
我构造出了F的无穷嵌套
I make an infinite series of F's.
我如果让它一直这样进行下去
If I just let this run forever,
我在外层就会得到越来越多的F
I'll just keep making more and more F's outside.
我运行一个无用的循环
I ran an infinite loop which is useless,
但内部是无用的并不重要
but it doesn't matter that the inside is useless.
因此 我们有 (Y F)=(F (Y F))
OK? So y of F is F applied to y of F.
Y组合子十分神奇
So y is a magical thing
如果把它应用于某个函数
which, when applied to some function,
它就会返回这个函数的不动点
produces the object which is the fixed point of that function,
当然是在不动点存在的前提下
if it exists, and if this all works.
这是因为 如果我把(Y F)带入F
Because, indeed, if I take y of F
结果还是(Y F)
I get y of F out.
现在我想让你们在
Now I want you to think this in terms of
EVAL-APPLY解释器方面思考一下
the eval-apply interpreter for a bit.
我在这里写了一大堆递归方程组
I wrote down a whole bunch of recursion equations out there.
那些联立方程组像
They're simultaneous in the same way
这些方程一样联立起来
these are simultaneous equations.
但EXPT不是联立方程
Exponentiation was not a simultaneous equation.
只是一个需要我赋义的变量
It was only one variable I was looking for a meaning for.
而Lisp则是某个过程的不动点
But what Lisp is is the fixed point of the process
对这个过程来说 如果我知道Lisp的定义
that's which says, if I knew what Lisp was
然后在递归方程等号的右边
and substituted it in for eval, and apply, and so on,
用它来代换EVAL、APPLY等变量
on the right hand sides of all those recursion equations,
如果它是一个良好定义的Lisp的话
then if it was a real good Lisp, is a real one,
那么递归方程等号左边 也是一个良好定义的Lisp
then the left hand side would also be Lisp.
这样 那个定义就讲得通了
So I made sense of that definition.
不过是否有解却不太明显
Now whether or not there's an answer isn't so obvious.
我也说不清
I can't attack that.
现在我要介绍的论证
Now these arguments that I'm giving you now
相当危险
are quite dangerous.
具体看这里
Let's look over here.
这些是关于极限的论证
On the. These are limit arguments.
我们要讨论的极限
We're talking about limits,
是微积分或者拓扑学的概念
and it's really calculus, or topology,
或者说是类似的 数学分析中的概念
or something like that, a kind of analysis.
这个论证是你们都承认的
OK？Now here's an argument that you all believe.
我想让你们意识到
And I want to make sure you realize
我可以把你们耍得团团转
that I could be bullshitting you.
准备好了吗？ 这是什么？
Alright? What is this?
u = 1 + 1/2 + 1/4 + .......
u is the sum of 1/2, 1/4, and 1/8, and so on,
这是几何级数求和
the sum of a geometric series.
当然 我也可以耍点小把戏
And, of course, I could play a game here.
u - 1 = 1/2 + 1/4 + 1/8 ......
u minus one is 1/2, plus 1/4, plus 1/8, and so on.
这里我可以
But now if I multiple. What I could do here--
糟糕了 这里漏掉了括号
Ooops. There is a parentheses error here.
这里应该是
But I can put here two times u minus one
2(u - 1) = 1 + 1/2 + 1/4 + 1/8 ........
is one plus 1/2, plus 1/4, plus 1/8.
这里能修改一下吗？
Can I fix that?
哦 可以
Yes, well.
看到了吗？
OK?
这样 我就得到
But that gives me back
2(u - 1) = u
two times u minus one is u,
因此我们推断出 u=2
therefore, we conclude that u is two.
这是正确的
And this actually is true.
这个推理过程没有问题
There's no problem like that.
但如果我要是做点别的什么呢？
But supposing I did something different.
假设我要求和的式子
Supposing I start up with something
明显没有和
which manifestly has no sum.
v = 1 + 2 + 4 + ........
v is one, plus two, plus four, plus 8, plus dot, dot, dot. OK?
v - 1 = 2 + 4 + 8 + ......
Well, v minus one is surely two, plus four, plus eight, plus dot, dot, dot. Right?
(v - 1)/2 = v
v minus one over two, gee, that looks like v again.
这里我就可以推断出
From that I should be able to conclude that--
显然这里又写错了
that's also wrong, apparently.
应该是 v = -1
v equals minus one.
这里应该是-1
That should be a minus one.
这个结论明显是错误的
And that's certainly a false conclusion.
当你处理极限的时候
So when you play with limits,
在某种方式下可行的论证
arguments that may work in one case
在其它情况下可能又不行了
they may not work in some other case.
要多加注意
You have to be very careful.
参数必须具有良好的形式
The arguments have to be well-formed.
但我不清楚 通常来说
And I don't know, in general,
像这样的论证有什么样的要求
what the story is about arguments like this.
我们要研习一大堆拓扑学文献来寻找答案
We can read a pile of topology and find out.
但是至少你们现在理解了
But, surely, at least you understand now,
为什么我们在黑板上写的这些东西
why it might be some meaning
是有一定语义的
to the things we've been writing on the blackboard.
你们也理解了它的语义
And you understand what that might mean.
我想现在是时候
So, I suppose, it's almost about time
祝贺你们成为
for you to merit being made a member
神圣的递归秩序中的
of the grand recursive order
一名LAMBDA演算黑客了
of lambda calculus hackers.
这是我们的徽章
I would. This is the badge.
因为你已经理解了
Because you now understand, for example,
它上面的那句话
what it says at the very top,
(Y F) = (F (Y F))
y F equals F y F.
这节课讲完了
Thank you.
有什么问题吗？
Are there any questions?
Lev 请说
Yes, Lev.
学生：目前的状况来看
AUDIENCE: With this, it seems that
正如你指出的那样 我们不再需要DEFINE
there's no need to define, as you imply,
不需要先存储一个值 以后再用
to just remember a value, to apply it later.
教授：对
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
学生：DEFINE在语言中好像有一些副作用
AUDIENCE: Defines were kind of a side-effect it seemed in the language.
（听不清）并且依赖于时序
[INTERPOSING] are order dependent.
不用DEFINE 是否消除了副作用？
Does this eliminate the side-effect from the.
教授： 实际上
PROFESSOR: Well. The answer is,
解释器并不是像这样实现的
this is not the way these things were implemented.
明白了吧？
OK?
在实际的实现中 DEFINE这个运算
Define, indeed is implemented as an operation
确实修改了环境
that actually modifies an environment structure,
改变了执行DEFINE的那个框架
changes the frame that the define is executed in.
这样做是有很多原因的
And there are many reasons for that,
其中之一就是
but a lot of this has to do with
方便交互式系统
making an interactive system.
就是说 如果你构造了一个系统
What this is saying is that if you've made a system,
而且你知道
and you know
你不打算进行调试
and you know you're not going to do any debugging
或之类的事儿
or anything like that,
你想立马知道所有的东西
and you know everything there is all at once,
你想知道的是
and you want to say,
方程组的最终解是什么？
what is the meaning of a final set of equations?
然后系统返回你相应的值
This gives you a meaning for it.
但如果想要让系统变成交互式的
But in order to make an interactive system,
这样你可以在不影响其它部分的情况下
where you can change the meaning of one
增量式地修改某一部分
without changing everything else, incrementally,
没有DEFINE的话 就不能这么做了
you can't do that by implementing it this way.
你说
Yes.
学生：就是那张“危险”的幻灯片
AUDIENCE: Another question on your danger slide.
好像你举的两个例子
It seemed that the two examples that you gave
与其收敛与否有关系？
had to do with convergence and non-convergence?
教授：是的
PROFESSOR: Right.
学生：函数理论中是否有
AUDIENCE: And that may or may not have something to do with
像线性系统
with function theory in a way which
或者非线性系统中的
would lead you to think of it in terms of linear systems,
那种思考方式
or non-linear systems.
函数的收敛性能否先验地知道
How does this convergence relate to being able to
哪些属性可能被违反？
see a priori what properties of that might be violated?
教授：我不知道
PROFESSOR: I don't know.
我也不知道它需要什么条件
The answer is, I don't know under what circumstances.
我不知道怎么在一节课内
I don't know how to translate that
就给你们讲清楚
into less than an hour of talk more.
有什么条件来判别它们
What are the conditions under which,
是否收敛？
for which we know that these things converge?
确实
And indeed,
这些都是为了告诉你 基于收敛的论证
all that was telling you that arguments that are based on convergence
都不可靠
are flaky
如果你事先不知道收敛性的话
if you don't know the convergence beforehand.
你可能做出错误的论证
You can make wrong arguments.
你可以先假设知道了答案 然后进行演绎
You can make deductions, as if you know the answer,
看它会不会产生什么明显的矛盾
and not be stopped somewhere by some obvious contradiction.
学生：我们是否可以说
AUDIENCE: So can we say then that
如果数学表达式F收敛
if F is a convergent mathematical expression,
那么它的递归性质就--
then the recursion property can be--
教授：我认为 在技术上有一类F
PROFESSOR: Well, I think there's a technical kind of F,
通过一些技术准则
OK? There is a technical description
我们可以找到这样的F
of those F's that have the property
当你像这样迭代地应用它们时
that when you iteratively apply them like this,
它一定会收敛
you converge.
这类准则包括：单调、连续
Things that are monotonic, and continuous,
我想想
OK?
我把其它的准则忘了
and I forgot what else.
还有一些列像这样的
There is a whole bunch of little conditions like that
判别准则
which have this property.
现在的难点是 给定F然后进行推理
Now the real problem is deducing from looking at the F,
这是F的定义
its definition here,
它满足这些准则吗？
whether not it has those properties,
这很难判断
and that's very hard.
那些准则都很简单得可以写下来
The properties are easy. You can write them down.
你可以看Joe Stoy写的一本书
You can look in a book by Joe Stoy.
那本书非常不错
It's a great book-- Stoy.
叫做The Scott-Strachey
It's called, The Scott-Strachey
《指称语义：基于Scott-Strachey方法》
The Scott-Strachey Method of Denotational Semantics,
作者是Joe Stoy
and it's by Joe Stoy,
由MIT出版社出版
MIT Press.
他把这一方面讲得非常详细
And he works out all this in great detail,
绝对会让你吓一大跳
enough to horrify you.
但是这本书仍然值得一读
But it really is readable.
好吧 谢谢大家
OK, well, thank you.
这节课到此为止
Time for the bigger break, I suppose.
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP